本片改编自2006到2011年间
发生在威尔士彭布罗克郡的真实警方调查
为了戏剧化的效果以及适当地保护匿名性
剧中的部分人物和事件有所改动
欢迎回家  亲爱的
Welcome home, love.
约翰  你有个不寻常的爱好
You've got an unusual hobby, John.
是的  水肺潜水
Oh, yes, the scuba diving.
那里是潜水的绝佳地点  不是吗
Apparently it's the place to do it down there, isn't it?
-我们有很长的海岸线  -没错
- Well, we've got the coastline. - Yes.
我们有深水区
'Well, we've got the deep water...
你也可以游过山脉之类的
And you can swim over mountains and all sorts.
是啊
Yeah.
报警电话  你需要什么服务
999, which service?
我妻子  她晕倒了
It's my wife. She's collapsed.
快派救护车来
I need an ambulence.
我叫约翰·库珀
My name is John Cooper.
彭布罗克郡谋杀案 第三集(剧终)
安雯
Anwen.
-好久没见  -史蒂夫
- Long time. - Steve.
我们照你说的做了  我们把库珀从现场带走
We've done as you asked, removed Cooper from the scene.
他正在哈弗福韦斯特警局录口供
He is giving a statement down at Haverfordwest Station.
医务人员把她放躺在了地上做心肺复苏
The paramedics put her on the floor for CPR.
我们需要叫内政部病理学家来给她尸检
We need the Home Office pathologist on this.
我去联系死因裁判官
I'll call the coroner.
安雯
And Anwen...
一定要让大家知道  这里可能不涉及到犯罪
make sure everyone knows it's possible there's no crime here.
对待库珀时  要向对待一个
Cooper should be treated as sensitively
刚失去妻子的丈夫那样体谅
as any husband who's just lost his wife.
没有挣扎迹象
There's no signs of a struggle.
手臂和脖颈没有瘀伤
No bruising on the arms or neck.
我们本可以阻止的
We could have prevented this.
病理学家出报告前
We won't know if he killed her
我们不能确定是不是他杀了她
until we get the pathologist's report.
在那之前  他不能回家去
Till then, he won't be allowed back in the house.
他要住在兄弟家
He's staying with his brother.
但这是个警告
But this is a warning.
约翰·库珀出来了  这绝没好事
John Cooper is out, and no good can come of that.
而且
And...
我们的行动随时可能被中止
we could be shut down any day.
所以我们不能光坐着
So, it's not good enough for us to sit around
等着鉴证证据的拯救
waiting for forensics to save our arses.
我们得主动出手
We have to make something happen.
那条卡其色短裤还不知在何处
Those khaki shorts are out there.
早
Morning.
你们前方是库珀最后的住址  玫瑰草地巷28号
Ahead of you is 28 Rose Meadow Lane, Cooper's last home.
你们后方是萨迪斯村
Behind you is Sardis village.
这里曾是他的猎杀地
This was his hunting ground.
那片田地他常去
Those fields were his rat runs.
感谢猎人行动  我们知道
And thanks to Huntsman, we know that
这些灌木篱墙是他所谓的"安全领地"
these hedgerows were his so-called "safes",
他会把他偷来的东西或作案工具埋藏在这里
where he hid items he'd stolen or his offending gear.
这条卡其色短裤在审讯中让他不安
Now, these khaki shorts worried him in the interviews.
他觉得这条短裤还在这里
He thinks they're out there still.
史蒂夫·威尔金斯  你好
Steve Wilkins, hello.
你好  威尔金斯先生  我是内政部的病理学家
Hello, Mr Wilkins. It's the Home Office pathologist here.
你好  先生
Hello, sir.
谢谢你这么快就给我回电
Thank you for getting back to me so promptly.
-是帕特·库珀尸检的结果  -嗯
- The results of Pat Cooper's postmortem. - Yeah?
她死于自然因素
She died of natural causes.
-自然因素  -对
- Natural causes? - Yes.
-显然是心脏衰竭  -心脏
- It was clearly heart failure. - Her heart?
好
Ok.
All right.
谢谢你回电  多谢了
Well, thank you for getting back. We appreciate it.
不客气
No problem.
她早料到了
She saw this coming.
她从报上剪下了一个广告
She had an ad cut out from the paper
是关于安排自己的葬礼的
about arranging your own funeral.
她早知道
She knew.
她知道他回来跟她住会要她的命
She knew living with him again would be the death of her.
你觉得他会尝试联系你吗
Do you think he'll try and make contact with you?
不可能
No chance.
那葬礼呢
What about the funeral?
他不会要我去的
He won't want me there.
那你想要什么呢
What about what you want?
如果你想参加你妈妈的葬礼  我们可以帮忙
If you want to attend your mother's funeral, we can help with that.
太麻烦了
Too much aggro.
我改日再自己去见她
I'll go see her in my own time.
安德鲁
Andrew...
我代表自己和团队
on behalf of my team and myself...
深表遗憾
I'm sorry.
不怪你
It wasn't your fault.
坏人身边出坏事
Bad things happen around bad men.
海军社交俱乐部有限公司
他说得对  史蒂夫
He's right, Steve.
这不怪我们
It wasn't our fault.
如果库珀还在监狱  帕特就不会死
If Cooper was still inside, Pat would still be alive
安德鲁就还有个妈妈
and Andrew would still have a mother.
但帕特不在了  他会更加危险
But with Pat out of the picture, he's even more dangerous.
就像颗定时炸弹
It's like a ticking time bomb.
独自居住对他来说是陌生领域
Living on his own is new territory for him.
只有他与他的思想独处
Just him and his thoughts.
还有他的幻想  冲动
His fantasies, compulsions.
积蓄了10年
Ten years' worth.
我们团聚在此  是为了将我们的姐妹帕特丽夏
We have come together to commend our sister Patricia
交到全能的上帝  天父手中
into the hands of Almighty God, our heavenly father.
面对死亡
In the presence of death,
基督徒有充分理由满怀希望与信心
Christians have sure grounds for hope and confidence,
甚至喜悦  因为主耶稣基督
and even joy, because the Lord Jesus Christ,
祂与我们生死与共
who shared our human life and death,
在光荣复活后永世长存
was raised again triumphant and lives evermore.
抱此信念
In this faith, we put our whole trust.
我们谦卑地恳求您  主  帮助我们
And help us, we humbly beseech thee, Lord.
阿门
Amen.
操
Fuck!
格林
Glyn...
猎人行动此前在他家中
Huntsman recovered all the items
找到了所有衣物  是吗
of clothing from the house, correct?
是的
Yeah, they did, yeah.
-他们把每件衣物都拍照存档了  -嗯
- And they photographed every item? - Yeah.
卡其色短裤
Khaki shorts.
是同一种款式
They're the same.
这张照片有点不对劲
There's something wrong with this picture.
颜色会不会因为后期处理和闪光灯而失真了
Could the colour be affected by the processing? The flash?
应该是的  而且这是张老照片
Yeah, I guess so. And it's an old picture.
我们得看看这条短裤到底是什么样
We need to see what these shorts actually look like.
天啊
Jesus Christ...
确实是卡其色的
They are khaki.
但要短很多
But they do look a lot shorter.
可能是他改短了
Maybe he had them altered.
帕特生前是裁缝
Pat was a seamstress.
请让我看看
May I?
史蒂夫  是松紧裤腰带  没有前裆开口
Oh, Steve, elasticated waistband. No fly.
这...
They...
这看着像是女士短裤
They look like women's shorts.
好吧  我们只有这条线索
Yeah, well, they're all we've got.
我们要送去检测
We're sending them in for testing.
史蒂夫·威尔金斯
Steve Wilkins.
史蒂夫  我是安吉拉·盖洛普
Steve, it's Angela Gallop.
你在开车吗
Are you driving, by any chance?
没关系  我开了外放
It's OK, you're on speaker.
你还是停车再接吧
I think you'd better pull over.
好了
Ok.
-什么事  -是这样
- What is it? - Right...
我们依你的要求拆去了短裤的缝边
So, we unpicked the hem of the shorts, like you asked,
用胶带采集了揭开部分的纤维
and we taped the uncovered area for fibres
发现了一处暗淡的污迹
and noticed there is a faint stain.
于是我们找回短裤上的那个地方...
So, we went back to the exact same spot on the shorts and...
发现了一小点血渍
...found a tiny flake of blood.
是彼得·迪克森的
It's Peter Dixon's.
-你有多少把握  -做了全套血检
- How sure are you? - Full profile.
那个血样是其他人的概率
The probability of that blood having come from anybody else
为十亿分之一
is a billion to one.
这是你的关键证据  史蒂夫
It's your golden nugget, Steve.
史蒂夫
Steve?
你还在听吗
Are you still there?
请别误会我的意思
Please, don't take this the wrong way...
但我好他妈爱你
...but I bloody love you!
指控他所有罪名
Charge him with the lot.
包括诺顿山吗
Including Nolton Hill?
-全部  -太好了
- The lot. - Yes!
谢谢
Thank you.
查他的车
Check the vehicle.
我们上
We're going in.
早啊  约翰
Morning, John.
约翰·威廉·库珀
John William Cooper,
你因涉嫌谋杀
you're under arrest for the murders
-海伦和理查德·托马斯被捕  -滚
- of Helen and Richard Thomas... - Fuck off!
-放开我  滚  -还有彼得和格温达·迪克森
- Get off me! Fuck off! - ...and Peter and Gwenda Dixon.
你还因涉嫌
You are also under arrest
在1996年于米尔福德港
for attempted armed robbery, rape and sexual assault
持枪抢劫  强奸  性侵害5名青少年被捕
during an attack on five teenagers in Milford Haven in 1996.
头儿
Boss...
天呐
Jesus...
我还在副驾储物箱找到了这个
And I found this in the glove compartment.
地形测量局
菲什加德和彭布罗克地图
我们及时抓住了他
We got him just in time.
好了  约翰
Right, John.
你认识理查兹督察
You know Detective Inspector Richards.
我是史蒂夫·威尔金斯警司
I am Detective Superintendent Steve Wilkins.
我知道你是谁
I know who you are.
你看得清楚吗  约翰
Can you see OK, John?
我准备了一副眼镜  以防你需要
I've got a spare pair of glasses if you need them.
这个是我
That's me.
那个不是
That isn't.
我们上次见面时
The last time we met, you said
你说你没留过及肩头发
you'd never had collar-length hair.
我忘了我20年前留过及肩头发  那又怎样
Oh, so I forgot that I had collar-length hair 20 years ago.
这不犯法吧
It's not a crime, is it?
我们聊聊画像里的男人穿的短裤  约翰
Let's talk about the shorts the man in the drawing's wearing, John.
向库珀先生出示证物AJM-165的照片
Mr Cooper is being shown a photo of item AJM/165.
是猎人行动在玫瑰草地巷2号找到的卡其色短裤
The khaki shorts recovered by Huntsman from 28 Rose Meadow Lane.
约翰  我们上次对话时
Now, the last time you spoke to us, John,
你说你有过一条
you said that you'd once owned a pair of
据你描述  卡其色的泳裤
what you described as khaki bathers.
就是这条吗
Is that them?
如果是在我家找到的  或许是吧
Well... if they're from my home, maybe.
严格来说  这不是泳裤  约翰
Strictly speaking, they're not bathers, John.
布料太沉了
The fabric's too heavy.
我当泳裤穿  所以对我来说就是泳裤
I used them as bathers. So, to me, that's what they are.
在2008年7月的讯问中
During the interview in July 2008,
你说画像中男人所穿的短裤
you said that the shorts worn by the man in the drawing
不可能是你的  因为你的泳裤更短
couldn't possibly be yours as your bathers were much shorter.
你自己看
See for yourself.
录音存证  我向库珀先生出示证物AJM-165-B
For the tape, I'm showing Mr Cooper item AJM/165/B.
我们拆了缝边  约翰
We unpicked the hem, John.
你看到了吗  把额外布料放下来后
So, do you see how, with the excess fabric turned down,
两条短裤的长度差距
the difference in length between
减小了
the two pairs of shorts is reduced?
你改任何一件衣物都会有这结果
If you do that to any garment, that's what'll happen.
我们知道你妻子以前是裁缝
Yeah, we know your wife used to work as a seamstress.
是她改了这条短裤吗
Did she alter these shorts?
别把我妻子扯进来
You leave my wife out of this.
自2008年7月的讯问之后
Since the July 2008 interviews,
法医鉴证又有了一些新发现
certain forensic discoveries have been made
我们想和你讨论一下
which we would like to discuss with you
让你有机会发表意见
so that you can have an opportunity to comment.
证物AJM-165-B
In reference to AJM/165/B,
在这个白圈圈起来的地方
this white circle indicates an area
发现了彼得·迪克森的血
where an amount of Peter Dixon's blood was found.
你能给我们解释下  这是怎么回事吗
Can you give us an explanation as to how that might be?
我大部分衣服都是帕特在乐施会和剩余军资商店买的
Pat got most of my clothes from the Oxfam and Army Surplus.
你们也该去问问我儿子
Oh, and you should also be talking to my son.
我之前告诉过你们了
As I told you all before,
他喜欢借我的衣服穿
he was in the habit of borrowing my clothes.
约翰
John...
彼得·迪克森的血
was Peter Dixon's blood
是不是在你枪杀他时留在卡其色短裤上的
deposited on the khaki shorts when you shot him?
-我这辈子从没杀过人  -这条短裤
- I've never killed anybody in my life. - These shorts...
抱歉  是泳裤
sorry, bathers...
堪称是宝库  约翰  特别是口袋里
were something of a treasure trove, John. Especially the pockets.
证物照片AJM-166
Photo AJM/166.
约翰  照片里显示的是在你卡其色短裤口袋里
What this photo shows us, John, is a microscopic image
找到的绒毛的显微图像
of the fluff found in the pockets of your khaki bathers.
该绒毛含有人类毛发  你的
Fluff that consisted of human hair. Yours.
还含有皮肤细胞  也是你的
Skin cells. Also yours.
但没有你儿子的
But nothing of your son, though.
在绒毛里还发现了某种织物纤维
Certain fabric fibres were also found in the fluff.
录音存证  BB-109手套
For the tape, glove BB/109,
在你位于玫瑰草地巷28号住处附近的
found under the hedgerow near your home
灌木篱墙底下找到的
at 28 Rose Meadow Lane.
MTJ-5和7
MTJ/5 and 7
由猎人行动在萨迪斯小路发现的
recovered by Huntsman from the Sardis trail.
约翰  这三只手套是你的吗
John, are these three gloves yours?
绝对不是
Absolutely not.
我说过了  我们家只有阿德里安戴手套
As I told you before, Adrian was the glove-wearer in our family.
我从来不戴手套  我觉得太累赘了
I never wore gloves. I found them too cumbersome.
那我们在你车储物箱里找到的新手套呢
What about the new pair we found in the boot of your car?
这个嘛
Well...
显然我现在戴手套了
obviously, I wear gloves now.
我老了  开始怕冷
Now I'm older, I feel the cold more.
在你卡其色泳裤口袋里的绒毛中
Fibres exactly matching the constituent fibres
发现了和这三只手套上
of these three gloves were found in the fluff
完全吻合的纤维
from the pockets of your khaki bathers.
-你对此作何解释  -你是聋了吗
- How do you account for that? - Are you deaf?
我说过了  阿德里安比我更常穿这条泳裤
I told you, Adrian wore the bathers more than me.
当两块布料互相接触时
When two articles of clothing come into contact with each other,
上面的纤维会发生交换
there is always an exchange of fibres.
在BB-109手套证物上
On glove BB/109,
我们的团队找到了来自他处的纤维
our team found fibres from another source.
录音存证  证物BM-1
For the tape, BM/1,
理查德·托马斯的一只袜子
a sock belonging to Richard Thomas.
1985年  斯科维斯顿公园的大火
The only item of clothing recovered from his body
烧毁了他的尸体  这是仅剩的一件衣物
after it was destroyed in the fire at Scoveston Park in 1985.
在BB-109手套证物上找到了这只袜子的纤维
Fibres from this sock were found on glove BB/109.
在这只袜子上也找到了手套上的纤维
And fibres from this glove were found on this sock.
约翰  你听明白了吗
Are you with me so far, John?
继续说吧  我知道你想说
Oh, keep talking, yeah. I know you want to.
这些发现与之前公认的推断吻合
These discoveries are consistent with the accepted view
杀害理查德·托马斯的凶手佩戴手套
that Richard Thomas' killer wore gloves
在斯科维斯顿公园  把理查德的尸体
when he dragged his body from the outbuilding
从外屋拖进了主屋
into the main house at Scoveston.
你听听他说的胡话
Are you listening to this, huh?
-简直在编故事  -约翰
- This is Fantasy Island. - John...
1985年12月  发生在斯科维斯顿公园的
are you the person responsible
理查德和海伦·托马斯谋杀案
for the murder of Richard and Helen Thomas
是不是你干的
at Scoveston Park in December 1985?
不是
No.
不是我
I was not.
约翰  纤维给了我们源源不断的信息
Fibres are the gifts that keep on giving, John.
在MTJ-5和7手套证物上
Other fibres, from a different source,
找到了不同来源的纤维
were found on gloves MTJ/5 and 7.
录音存证  证物BKG-9
For the tape, BKG/9.
这些纤维与1996年3月6日晚
Those fibres were an exact match
在米尔福德港  诺顿山住宅区附近的田野上
with constituent fibres found in the underwear of a young female
被强奸的一名年轻女性内衣里
who was raped on the evening of the 6th March 1996
发现的成分纤维完全吻合
in a field by the Nolton Hill Estate, Milford Haven.
约翰  1996年3月6日当天于诺顿山
John, are you the person who, on 6th March 1996,
你是否用枪胁迫了5名年轻人
pointed a gun at five young people,
其中三名女性  两名男性
three females and two males, on Nolton Hill
并且搜刮了他们身上的财物
and searched them for money?
库珀先生并未作答
Mr Cooper has not answered.
约翰  你是否强奸了其中一位年轻女性
John, are you the person who raped one of the young females?
库珀先生并未作答
Mr Cooper has not answered.
约翰  你是否猥亵了
John, are you the person who indecently assaulted
她们之中的另一位年轻女性
one of the other young females?
录音存证
For the tape...
证物PH-2  萨迪斯小路上找到的锯短猎枪
PH/2, the sawn-off shotgun found on the Sardis trail,
与在诺顿山袭案中
which matches the description
两名受害者的描述完全吻合
given by two of the victims of the Nolton Hill attack,
也与萨迪斯劫案中受害者的描述吻合
and the victim in the Sardis robbery,
该案已于1998年宣判你有罪
a crime we know you were convicted of in 1998.
如果你想说那上面有我的DNA  我告诉过她了
If you're gonna say that you found my DNA on that, I told her...
在审判时  公诉律师让我拿过枪
about the prosecution making me handle it during the trial.
约翰  我们确实在枪上找到了DNA
Well, we did find DNA on the gun, John.
但不是你的DNA
But not yours.
你看到枪管和枪柄上的黑色抛光面了吗
You see the black finish on the barrel and stock?
安维林牌缎黑金属漆
Anvileen satin black metal paint.
录音存证  证物JAW-100
For the tape, JAW/100,
猎人行动在玫瑰草地巷28号的棚屋中找到的
recovered by Huntsman from the shed at 28 Rose Meadow Lane.
约翰
John...
是你在枪管上涂了油漆吗
were you the one who applied this paint to the barrel of the gun?
那不是
That is not...
我的枪
my gun.
我们把油漆弄掉了
We had the paint removed.
在一些油漆碎片上  我们的法医
On some of the flakes, our forensic scientists
注意到一些红色斑点  经检测为血液
noticed a reddish cast that tested positive for blood.
彼得·迪克森的血
Peter Dixon's blood.
约翰
John...
是你用这把枪射杀了彼得和格温达·迪克森吗
did you shoot Peter and Gwenda Dixon with this gun?
-约翰  你干什么  -约翰
- What are you doing, John? - John...
约翰  坐下
Sit down, John.
诺顿山住宅区
艾琳·詹姆斯
Erin James?
是艾琳·戴维斯  我结婚了
Erin Davies. I'm married.
你好  艾琳
Hi, Erin.
我是艾拉·理查兹督察
I'm Detective Inspector Ella Richards.
这位是史蒂夫·威尔金斯警司
This is Detective Superintendent Steve Wilkins.
我记得你
Mm, I remember you.
艾琳  我们最近逮捕了一个人
Erin, we've recently arrested a man
怀疑他杀了四个人
on suspicion of committing four murders.
我们还确信就是他在1996年袭击了你和你朋友
We also believe he was the man who attacked you and your friends in 1996.
过了这么久才抓到
After all this time?
我非常抱歉  我明白这一定令你很震惊
I'm so sorry. I realise this must be a shock.
你们十三年前怎么没把案破了
Why couldn't you have done this 13 years ago?
艾琳...
Erin...
我能说句话吗
may I say something?
我们明白  我们让你失望了
We know we let you down.
我们只想确保伤害过你和你朋友的人
All we want is to see to it the man who hurt you and your friends
不会再有机会去伤害其他人
never gets to hurt anyone else ever again.
你可以协助做到这一点
And you can help make that happen.
我们会给你们指派家庭联络员
All of you will be assigned Family Liaison Officers
在这过程中给予你和家人支持
to support you and your family through the process.
庭审还要好几周后才开始
The trial won't be for weeks yet.
我不会参加庭审
I won't be taking part in any trial.
你们都不需要在法庭上露面
None of you will be required to appear in court.
一切都可以通过视频连线进行
Everything will be done via video link.
你不用和他出现在同一个房间里
You won't have to be in the same room as him.
我丈夫不知道我被强奸过
My husband doesn't know I was raped.
1989年6月29日  双尸案
诺顿山住宅区袭击案  1996年3月6日  强奸和性侵害
情况如何
How was it?
黎安·当西会作证
Leanne Dauncey will testify.
艾琳很生气  但黎安觉得她能说服她
Erin's angry, but Leanne thinks she can talk her round.
凯伦·约瑟夫不可能了  她根本出不了门
Karen Joseph's out of the question. She's practically housebound.
从受袭后她就一直有精神方面的问题
She's had mental health issues ever since the attack.
两个男孩也不愿意配合
The two boys won't cooperate, either.
因为最初调查时所发生的那些事
Not after everything that happened with the original investigation.
庭审于明天在斯旺西刑事法院开始
The trial begins at Swansea Crown Court tomorrow
被告人为65岁来自彭布罗克郡
'of 65-year-old John William Cooper
《今夜威尔士》
乔纳森·希尔报道
莱特斯顿的约翰·威廉·库珀
of Letterston, Pembrokeshire.
库珀被控杀害四人
'Cooper has been charged with the four murders
以及1996年在米尔福德港
'and with the rape and indecent assault
强奸和猥亵两名未成年少女
'of two teenage girls at Milford Haven in 1996.'
辩方会大肆围绕那条卡其色短裤
The defence will make much of the fact that the khaki shorts
其实是女士短裤这事做文章
are indeed women's shorts.
会说被告残忍杀害迪克森夫妇时
That it makes no sense that the defendant was wearing them
穿着它是完全不合逻辑的
when he brutally murdered Mr and Mrs Dixon.
但凶杀案往往与常识相悖
But murder cases have a habit of defying common sense.
据迪克森夫妇的儿子所说...
According to the son of Mr and Mrs Dixon...
他父母只要出去散步
..whenever his parents went walking
而他母亲穿着长裤时
and his mother was wearing long trousers,
她都会在背包里放一条短裤
she would always put a pair of shorts in her backpack
以防天气变暖
in case the weather turned warm.
但在海岸小径案的犯罪现场
But no shorts of any description were found
没找到任何短裤
at the Coastal Path crime scene.
为什么呢
Why?
女士们先生们  想想事发的先后顺序吧
Imagine the sequence of events, ladies and gentlemen.
被告近距离枪杀了迪克森夫妇
The defendant shoots the Dixons at close range.
然后他搬动了尸体并用树枝掩盖
He then moves their bodies and covers them with branches.
在这过程里  他们的血...
In the process, some of their blood -
从这些可怕的照片来看  很可能是大量的血
judging by these distressing images, probably a lot of their blood -
弄到了他的裤子上
gets onto his trousers.
恐慌中  他翻了受害人的背包  并发现了...
In a panic, he goes through his victims' backpacks and finds...
迪克森太太的卡其色短裤
..Mrs Dixon's khaki shorts.
他脱掉自己沾了血的裤子
He removes his own blood-stained trousers
换上迪克森太太的短裤  带着他的裤子
and puts on Mrs Dixon's shorts and quits the scene,
离开现场  并未注意到有一滴
taking his trousers with him, unaware that a single spot
彼得·迪克森的血弄到了短裤上
of Peter Dixon's blood had found its way onto the shorts.
你怎么没在里面
How come you're not inside?
本案的高级调查员是控方最后的证人
The SIO is the last Crown witness.
作证之前我不能进去
I'm not allowed in until I give my evidence.
你感觉如何
How are you feeling?
完全准备好了
Ready as I'll ever be.
来吧
Come on.
这幅警方画像是根据一位
This police artist's impression was based
看到被告使用彼得·迪克森的银行卡
on a witness sighting of the defendant as he withdrew cash
在哈弗福韦斯特的西敏寺银行自动取款机上
from a NatWest ATM in Haverfordwest
提取现金的目击者描述所画的
using Peter Dixon's bank card.
目击发生在案发两天之后  不可思议的是
The sighting was made two days after the murder and yet, incredibly,
被告居然仍穿着迪克森太太的短裤
the defendant was still wearing Mrs Dixon's khaki shorts.
这一将他与两起谋杀联系在一起的重大证据
A hugely incriminating piece of evidence linking him to two murders.
他为什么不尽快
Why on earth had he not disposed of them
将这条裤子丢弃
at the earliest opportunity?
诸位想想这说明了约翰·威廉·库珀是怎样的心态
Think about what that says about the mind of John William Cooper.
他是在蔑视全世界吗
Was he thumbing his nose at the world,
坚信自己非常聪明  犯下如此恶行也不会被抓吗
convinced that he was too clever to be caught for his horrific crime?
还是他有更阴暗  更奇怪的动机
Or was his motivation darker, stranger?
他是否把迪克森太太的短裤当做战利品自豪地穿着
Did he regard Mrs Dixon's shorts as a trophy to be worn with pride...
也许还有一些性满足
..and perhaps just a touch of sexual gratification?
无论何种解释  这幅画展现了一个杀手
Whatever the explanation, this drawing shows a killer
正穿着从被他残忍杀死的
wearing an item of clothing stolen
女人那里偷来的衣服
from a woman he has murdered in cold blood.
被告一直坚称
The defendant has always maintained
这幅画与1989年夏天的自己
that this drawing bears no resemblance to himself
无任何相似之处
as he was in the summer of 1989.
但相当巧合的是
But due to an extraordinary quirk of fate,
海岸小径谋杀案发生前一个月
one month before the Coastal Path murders,
他的样子在他参加一档
his likeness was captured on video
全国播出的游戏节目时被视频记录了下来
during his appearance on a game show on national television.
从中截出的图像就是有力的证明
The resulting image speaks volumes.
你坐这里
This is you.
他能看见你  但你看不见他
Now, he can see you. But you can't see him.
还有  提醒你一句
And, er... be warned.
他的出庭律师会对你态度恶劣
His defence barrister will be rough with you.
他会试图把你描述为对他心怀怨念
He'll try and paint you as the unreliable witness
不可靠的证人
with an axe to grind.
别担心  史蒂夫
No worries, Steve.
我有龙鳞  能保护自己
I've got my dragon scales for protection.
请陪审团重新入席
'Let's have the jury back in, please.'
双方律师都会称呼你为阿德里安
Both the barristers will refer to you as Adrian.
这只是为了不让陪审团搞混
That's just so the jury doesn't get confused.
没问题
No problem.
埃文斯先生  你可以开始交叉讯问了吗
'Mr Evans, are you content to begin your cross-examination...?'
你为什么要改名
Why did you change your name?
因为是他叫我阿德里安的
Cos he was the one that called me Adrian.
那时这更像是女孩的名字
It was more of a girl's name back then.
你知道约翰尼·卡什那首《名叫苏的男孩》吗
You know that Johnny Cash song, A Boy Named Sue?
他过去常放那首歌
He played it constantly.
"阿德里安  他们在放你的歌"
"Adrian, they're playing your song."
他说他给我取个女孩名字
He said he called me a girl's name
是出于和歌里那位父亲相同的原因
for the same reason as the father in the song.
让我变得坚韧
To toughen me up...
因为我将不得不去反抗
..cos I'd have to fight.
也许这件事他做对了
Maybe it's the one thing he got right.
我就是个固执的混蛋
I'm a stubborn bastard.
这是真的吗  阿德里安
Isn't it true, Adrian,
当你住在玫瑰草地巷28号时
that when you were living at 28 Rose Meadow Lane
经常会穿你父亲的衣服
you often used to wear your father's clothes?
不  我从没穿过他的衣服
No, I never wore his clothes.
那手套呢  阿德里安
What about gloves, Adrian?
你是家里唯一戴手套的人  这是真的吗
Isn't it true that you were the glove-wearer of the family?
我过去常戴手套  但他也戴
I used to wear gloves. But so did he.
你说的"他"是指谁
And who do you mean by "he"?
约翰·库珀
John Cooper.
你父亲吗
Your father?
是的  先生
Yes, sir.
这是真的吗  阿德里安  从11岁起
Isn't it true, Adrian, that from the age of 11
你在学校和家里都开始变得不听话
you started to become disobedient both at home and at school?
是的  也许有点
Yes, a bit, maybe.
你的不听话逐渐升级为盗窃  对吗
Your disobedience developed into theft, did it not,
偷你父亲和母亲的钱
stealing money from your mother and father?
不是
No!
我从没偷过我父母的钱  我不是小偷
I never stole any money from my parents. I'm not a thief.
迪克森夫妇遇害几天后
A few days after the murders of Mr and Mrs Dixon,
一枚黄金戒指被卖给了彭布罗克郡港口的珠宝行
a gold band was sold to a jewellers in Pembroke Dock,
控方声称该戒圈
which the prosecution claim
是凶手从彼得·迪克森尸体上取走的婚戒
was the wedding ring the killer removed from Peter Dixon's corpse.
珠宝行记录了这笔交易
The transaction was recorded by the jeweller
收据上的签名为J·库珀
on a receipt bearing the signature J Cooper.
法庭已听到你父亲
The court has heard that your father,
约翰·威廉·库珀  称该签...
John William Cooper, stated that the sig...
珠宝行的收据不是...
..jeweller's receipt was not...
他签名的通常形式为JW·库珀
..and that the usual form of his signature is JW Cooper.
这是真的吗  阿德里安  你住在
Isn't it true, Adrian, that when you lived at...
玫瑰草地巷28号时  你经常
'28 Rose Meadow Lane, you were in'
伪造你父亲和母亲的签名
the habit of forging the signatures of both your mother and father
目的是冒充他们的名义兑现支票
for the purpose of fraudulently cashing cheques in their names?
不  根本不是这样的
No, that's totally untrue.
你否认你当时能熟练伪造
You deny that you were an accomplished forger
你父亲和母亲的签名吗
of both your mother and father's signature?'
我听不见你在说什么
I can't hear what you're saying.
是听不见  还是故意说听不见  阿德里安
Can't hear or refuse to hear, Adrian?
抱歉  埃文斯先生  我们这端有点技术问题
Sorry, Mr Evans, we're having a technical issue this end.
你的声音断断续续的  请稍等一会
Your voice keeps cutting out. One minute, please.
继续吧  埃文斯先生  现在应该好了
Carry on, Mr Evans. It should be OK now.
我是这么认为的  阿德里安
'I put it to you, Adrian,
出于一些只有你知道的原因
'that for reasons known only to yourself,
你对你父亲一直怀有强烈的报复心
you have long' harboured a passionate vendetta against your father.
因为这种报复心
'That, because of this vendetta,'
你在和参与猎人行动
in your dealings with the police
和渥太华行动的警察接触时
in both the Huntsman and the Ottawa investigations,
你竭尽所能
you have done everything in your power
协助那些一心想迫害你父亲的警察
'to assist them in their singled-minded persecution' of your father.
甚至你将这次出庭视为
Indeed, that you see your appearance in court today as merely
一个可以散播更多谣言的机会
'another opportunity to spread more lies.'
你以为我真想来这吗
Do you really think I want to be here?
艾琳  黎安  感谢你们能来
Erin, Leanne, thank you for coming.
这是我们的父母还有艾琳的丈夫
These are our parents and Erin's husband.
我们会带你们去提供证词的房间
Er, we'll show you to the room you'll be giving your evidence from.
我们已经决定上庭作证了
We've decided to give our evidence in court.
凯伦去世了
Karen died.
发生了什么
What happened?
她的身体...
Her health...
最终还是撑不住了
finally gave out.
-我们要为她这么做  -是的
- We're doing this for her. - Yeah.
-还有斯蒂芬和大卫  -没错
- And Steven and David. - Yeah.
你还好吗
are you ok?
这里有纸巾和水
Tissues and water.
我们经常在我们住宅区旁的
We often played in the woods...
森林里玩
by our estate.
那里有个绳子秋千
There was a rope swing.
所以我们就在那消磨时间
So, we were mucking about on that.
大约...
About...
晚上八点天黑了  所以我们准备回家
eight o'clock it got dark, so we headed home.
我们走捷径  横穿农场
We took the shortcut across the farmer's field.
大约走到一半时  我们听到了声响
We were about halfway along when we heard a noise.
我们都回了头...
We all turned round...
看到有人朝我们走来  用手电筒照我们的眼睛
and saw someone coming towards us, shining a torch in our eyes.
我以为他是我们认识的男生  所以我对他喊...
I thought it was a boy we knew, so I shouted at him...
"你怎么不对着我们的眼睛晃啊  马丁"
.."Shine the light in our eyes, why don't you, Martin?"
但回答我们的是一个男人的声音
But the person shouted back in a man's voice...
"我长得像马丁吗"
.."Do I look like Martin?"
我们都以为他是农场主人
We all thought it was the farmer then.
但是...
But, erm...
随着他越走越近  我们看到他戴着面罩
as he came closer, we could see he had a mask on over his head with...
只露出了嘴和眼睛...
holes for the mouth and eyes...
他拿用一把猎枪指着我们
and er, he had a shotgun pointing at us.
大卫开始为我们进入了他农场向他道歉
Er, David started to apologise to the man for us being on his land.
那人叫他闭嘴
The man told him to shut up
然后他...
and er, he...
用猎枪击打了他的头部
hit him over the head with the shotgun.
然后...
And, erm...
大卫开始哭
..David started crying then.
后来他让我们走到农场地势较低的地方
And then he told us to walk down to the lower part of the field,
从住宅区看不见那里
which you can't see from the estate.
他...
He...
强迫我们说自己的名字
made us say our names.
他的语气很愤怒
His voice was angry.
我们都吓坏了
We were all really scared.
然后他叫我们趴在地上...
And then he told us to lie down on the ground...
把脸贴在草地上
..and keep our faces in the grass.
然后我感觉到...
And then I felt him...
他把我的头发撩到后面
pulling my hair at the back.
他叫我站起来
He told me to stand up...
跟他走
..and to go with him.
戴维斯太太  你和你朋友们的痛苦经历
Mrs Davies, the ordeal that you and your friends suffered
发生在1996年3月6日的晚上
on the evening of 6th March 1996
也就是15年前
happened 15 years ago.
你当时是个16岁的女孩
You were a girl of 16.
是的
Yeah.
你当时很害怕  天也黑了
You were terrified. It was dark.
综上所诉  你认为你对当时
Given all that, how reliable do you think your memory is
发生事件的记忆有多可靠
of the events which took place?
我对每个细节都记忆犹新
I remember every detail like it was yesterday.
这种事不可能忘
You don't forget something like that.
你试图忘记
You try to.
但是忘不掉
But you can't.
袭击你的人摘掉过面罩吗
Did the man who attacked you ever remove his mask?
没有
No.
那我确认下
So, to be clear...
你或你朋友都没看到过他的脸
..at no time did you, or any of your friends, see his face?
是的
No.
照片中的男子是真正的约翰·库珀
This man in the photograph is the real John Cooper.
一个和妻子结婚42年的忠诚丈夫
A loving husband who was married to his wife for 42 years.
我们的儿子曾是我们的掌上明珠
We had a son who was the apple of our eye.
然后这颗明珠腐坏  伤了他母亲的心
An apple that went bad and broke his mother's heart.
我认为我妻子心脏病发而死
I believe that the heart attack that killed my wife
是因为她一直以来承受了
was brought on because of the...
压力  悲伤和耻辱
the stress, the sadness and the shame
因为我明明无辜却遭到牢狱之灾
because of all the time that I spent in prison as an innocent man.
警方和伊利亚斯先生告诉你们  我是骗子
The police and Mr Elias tell you I'm a liar.
说我谎称我大多数衣服
That I'm lying when I say that most of my clothes,
尤其是我的卡其色泳裤是二手的
most significantly, my khaki bathers, were second-hand.
显然  他们无法体会贫穷的滋味
Well... obviously, they don't know what it's like to be poor.
我今天穿的西服是二手的
This suit that I'm wearing today, it's second-hand.
我家的衣柜里
In my wardrobe at home,
有一件二手大衣
I've got an overcoat second-hand
我穿去参加了我妻子的葬礼
that I wore to my wife's funeral.
陪审团的女士们先生们  我为了我没有犯下的罪行
Ladies and gentlemen of the jury, I spent ten years of my life
在牢里待了十年
in prison for crimes that I did not commit.
千万不要让警方
Please... Please, do not allow the police
再次让我遭遇不公的审判
to carry out another miscarriage of justice against me.
我不是杀人犯
I am not a murderer.
我不是强奸犯
I am not a rapist.
我是个被冤枉的无辜者  谢谢
I am an innocent man who's been wronged. Thank you.
伊利亚斯先生
Mr Elias...
还差一刻钟到4点
it's a quarter to four.
或许该休庭了
This would probably be a suitable time for me to rise.
你愿意明天再开始对库珀先生
Are you content to begin your cross-examination
进行交叉讯问吗
of Mr Cooper tomorrow?
如果大人允许的话
If My Lord would permit,
我想跟库珀先生谈几分钟
I would like to have a few minutes with Mr Cooper.
-好吧  伊利亚斯先生  -谢谢大人
- Very well, Mr Elias. - Thank you, My Lord.
库珀先生
All right, Mr Cooper...
我想问你几个问题
I would like to ask you a few questions about
关于在萨迪斯抢劫案现场附近的
the balaclava which was discovered
灌木篱墙下发现的黑头套
under the hedgerow near the scene of the Sardis robbery.
女士们先生们  你们肯定记得
Ladies and gentlemen, you will remember
这顶黑头套
that this is the balaclava which,
就是猎人行动审讯中那顶头套
in the course of the Huntsman trial,
在其中
it was found that
发现了不少被告的头发
there were a number of the defendant's head hairs within it.
请把MTJ-14证物给库珀先生
Could you please give Mr Cooper exhibit MTJ/14, please?
没事的  库珀先生
It's all right, Mr Cooper.
法医已经取完证了
The item has been cleared forensically.
触摸它不会给你造成麻烦
Touching it won't compromise you in any way.
库珀先生
Mr Cooper...
那是你的黑头套吗
is that your balaclava?
据我所知
To the best of my knowledge.
是还是不是  库珀先生
Yes or no, Mr Cooper?
是的  但萨迪斯抢劫案不是我干的
Yes. But I did not commit the Sardis robbery.
我说过  帽子在灌木篱墙下被发现之前
Like I said, that was stolen off my boat
早就从我的船上被偷走了
long before it was found under the hedgerow.
但你承认那黑头套是你的
But you accept that the balaclava is yours?
是的
Yes.
库珀先生  你在1998年的猎人行动审讯中
Mr Cooper, that isn't what you told
跟陪审团可不是这么说的  对吗
the jury during the Huntsman trial in 1998, is it?
我知道  我犯了错
I know. I made a mistake.
在那次庭审中  在宣誓之后
During that trial, under oath,
你否认那顶黑头套是你的
you denied that the balaclava was yours.
所以我要问你的是  库珀先生
So, my question to you, Mr Cooper,
你是当时对陪审团说了谎
is were you lying to the jury then...
-还是你现在在对陪审团说谎  -我不是骗子
- or are you lying to the jury now? - I'm not a liar.
-我忘了  我犯了错  -我重新组织下问题
- I forgot. I made a mistake. - Let me rephrase the question.
真相到底是什么
What was the truth?
你于1998年告诉陪审团的
What you told the jury in 1998
还是今天告诉陪审团的
or what you've told the jury today?
不  我不是故意...
No, I didn't deliberately...
我记错了
I misremembered.
1998年记错了  还是今天记错了  库珀先生
Misremembered in 1998 or misremembered today, Mr Cooper?
库珀先生
Mr Cooper...
问题很简单
the question is a simple one.
是哪个
Which was it?
1998年你在法庭上陈述的
What you said to the court in 1998
还是今天在法庭上陈述的
or what you have told us today?
今天
Today.
所以你承认1998年你对陪审团说谎了
So, you admit that in 1998 you lied to that jury?
-对  但是...  -谢谢  法官大人
- Yes, but... - Thank you, My Lord.
那么
So...
陪审团的各位
..members of the jury...
现在该让你们退下商讨判决结果了
..it is now time for you to retire to consider your verdicts.
请记住  无论何时  你们必须牢记
Remember, at all times, you must keep in mind
公诉方的职责是证明
that it is for the Crown to prove
约翰·威廉·库珀有罪
the guilt of John William Cooper...
而不是让被告证明自己无罪
..not for the defence to prove his innocence.
如果公诉方无法证明其有罪  那你们必须判决他
If the Crown have failed to do that, then you must find him...
有罪
无罪
not guilty.
-你还好吗  -嗯
- All right? - Yeah.
那些是什么
What are those?
我为媒体准备的判后发言稿
That's my post-verdict statements for the press.
有罪  无罪
Guilty. Not guilty.
你可以把那个扔了
Well, you can get rid of that one.
无罪
那是我的辞呈
That's my letter of resignation.
什么
What?
如果他被判无罪  那我就辜负了受害者和其家人
I'd have failed the victims and their families.
判决出来了
Verdict.
全体起立
All rise!
无论判决是什么
'Whatever the judgment is...
我们都带着尊严接受
we receive it with dignity.'
艾拉  林恩  格林  奈杰尔  兰博
Ella, Lynne, Glyn, Nigel, Rambo,
与你们共事是我的荣幸和光荣
it's been an honour and a privilege.
-谢谢  头儿  -谢谢  头儿
- Cheers, boss. - Cheers, boss.
请陪审团进来吧
Let's have the jury in, please.
首席陪审员请起立
Will the foreman please stand?
被告请起立
Will the defendant please stand?
法官大人  陪审团共商议了
My Lord, the jury has been in retirement
-八小时十分钟  -谢谢
- for eight hours and ten minutes. - Thank you.
首席陪审员先生  请用是或否回答我的问题
Mr Foreman, please answer my next question yes or no.
你们是否得出了一致通过的判决
'Have you reached a verdict on which you are all agreed?'
是
Yes.
11项罪状是否均达成了一致
Is that in relation to all 11 counts?
是
Yes.
起诉书的第一项罪状  谋杀海伦·托马斯
On count one of the indictment, the murder of Helen Thomas,
你们认为被告  约翰·威廉·库珀
do you find the defendant, John William Cooper,
有罪  还是无罪
guilty or not guilty?
-有罪  -有罪
- Guilty. - Guilty.
起诉书的第二项罪状
On count two of the indictment,
谋杀理查德·托马斯  有罪还是无罪
the murder of Richard Thomas, guilty or not guilty?
-有罪  -有罪
- Guilty. - Guilty.
起诉书的第三项罪状
On count three of the indictment,
谋杀格温达·迪克森  有罪还是无罪
the murder of Gwenda Dixon, guilty or not guilty?
有罪
Guilty.
起诉书的第四项罪状
On count four of the indictment,
谋杀彼得·迪克森  有罪还是无罪
the murder of Peter Dixon, guilty or not guilty?
有罪
Guilty.
起诉书的第五项罪状
On count five of the indictment,
强奸艾琳·戴维斯  娘家姓詹姆斯
the rape of Erin Davies, 'nee James...
有罪还是无罪
'..guilty or not guilty?'
-有罪  -胡扯
- Guilty. - Rubbish!
一派胡言
'That's rubbish!'
我不会强奸儿童
I'm not a child rapist!
这不公正
This is not justice!
起诉书的第六项罪状
On count six of the indictment,
猥亵黎安·当西
the indecent assault of Leanne Dauncey,
有罪还是无罪
guilty or not guilty?
-有罪  -胡扯
- 'Guilty.' - 'This is rubbish!'
你们没听到所有证据
You've not heard all the evidence!
这是诬陷  这不公正
This is a fit-up! This is not justice!
库珀先生  请安静  否则我将你驱逐出庭
Mr Cooper, be quiet, or I will have you removed.
我们爱你  约翰
We love you, John!
第七  八  九  十和十一项罪状
On counts seven, eight, nine, ten and 11,
抢劫未遂  有罪还是无罪
the offences of attempted robbery, guilty or not guilty?
有罪
Guilty.
约翰·威廉·库珀
John William Cooper,
陪审团裁决  你十一项罪名全部成立
the jury have found you guilty of all 11 counts on the indictment.
闭嘴  你个蠢猪
Shut up, you stupid bastard!
我在此宣判你无期徒刑
I hereby sentence you to life imprisonment.
你被判有罪的罪行
The crimes for which you have been convicted
邪恶至极  你被判处强制性终身监禁...
are of such evil wickedness, the mandatory sentence of life...
-这不公正  -...将严格执行
- This is not justice! - ..will mean just that.
-我是无辜的  -带他下去
- I'm an innocent man! - Take him down.
这不公正
This is not justice!
这是迫害
This is persecution!
史蒂夫·威尔金斯对约翰·库珀实施的迫害
Persecution of John Cooper, carried out by Steve Wilkins!
一个男人要为他没犯过的罪
A man is gonna spend time in prison
蒙冤入狱
for a crime he did not commit!
我不是强奸犯  我不是杀人犯
I am not a rapist! I am not a murderer!
这是诬陷
This is a fit-up!
我不是杀人犯
I am not a murderer!
今天的判决为理查德和海伦·托马斯
Today's verdicts give the families of Richard and Helen Thomas,
彼得和格温达·迪克森
Peter and Gwenda Dixon,
还有诺顿山袭击案的五名受害者及其家人
and the five victims of the Nolton Hill attack
主持了公道
and their families justice.
但无论法庭对约翰·威廉·库珀
But there is no sentence the court could have imposed
作出什么判决
on John William Cooper
都无法弥补他们失去至亲的痛苦
that could ever compensate them for their loss.
今天的裁决对所有会犯下这种
Today's verdicts are a warning to all individuals
可怕罪行的人都是个警告
who would commit such terrible crimes.
不管他们接触过什么
Whatever they touch...
都会留下对自己不利的证据
..will bear witness against them.
证据不会消失
Evidence lasts.
不会遗忘
It does not forget.
也不能说谎
And it cannot lie.
只要有决心  总会找到证据
And it will always be found by those with the will to find it.
谢谢
Thank you.
我代表达费德郡警局
On behalf of Dyfed Powys Police,
向渥太华行动的成员致敬
I would like to pay tribute to the officers of Operation Ottawa
感谢他们的不懈努力和专业精神
for their diligence and their professionalism.
你准备好报道独家新闻了吗  希尔先生
Are you ready for your exclusive, Mr Hill?
谢了  史蒂夫
Thanks, Steve.
-好了吗  -嗯
- Are we good? - Yeah.
警司
Detective Superintendent,
你对今天的判决有什么看法
can I get your reaction to today's sentencing?
-是啊  很好  -很漂亮
- Yeah, really great. - Really nice.
-是啊  状况很好  -非常棒
- Yeah? Brilliant. - Yeah, it's amazing.
很好  给你钱
Great. It's all here.
-他很喜欢吗  -是的
- He loves it? - Yeah.
很好  归你了
Awesome. It's all yours.
-非常感谢  -开得开心
- Much appreciated. - Enjoy.
我会照料好车子的  我保证
I'll look after it, I promise.
谢了
Thanks.
警探准则
没有比一个人调查另一个人的死因
更重大的责任和义务
头儿
Boss...
楼下有人找你
Visitor for you downstairs.
什么情况
Hey, what's this?
-你不是在学校吗  -对  我下午请假了
- I thought you were in school? - Yeah, I got the afternoon off.
想过来看看这一切发生的地方
I thought I'd come and see where it all happened.
现在没多少东西可看了
Well, there's not much to see now.
没有比一个人
"There is no greater responsibility or duty
调查另一个人的死因
placed on a human being than to investigate
更重大的责任和义务
"the circumstances of the death of another human being."
很能描述这份职业吧
Quite the job description, eh?
我决定不念高中了
I've decided sixth form's not for me.
你接受吗
Are you OK with that?
-你妈妈知道吗  -知道
- Does your mother know? - Yeah.
她怪你
She blames you.
不意外
Of course she does.
我想加入警队
I'm thinking of joining the police.
认真的吗
Seriously?
那你不踢足球了
What about the football?
得了吧  爸爸
Ah, come on, Dad.
我虽然优秀  但也没那么优秀
I'm good, but I'm not that good.
你凭什么觉得你当警察就能做得更好
What makes you think you'd be any better as a policeman?
你都能当得这么成功  能有多难
You made a success of it. How hard can it be?
别耍嘴皮子
Watch it!
帕特丽夏·玛格丽特·库珀
1945年2月7日-2008年12月2日
过早离开我的爱妻
我该留下来的
I should've stayed.
我们该好好谈谈的
We should've talked.
对不起  妈
I'm sorry, Ma.
改编自史蒂夫·威尔金斯和乔纳森·希尔所著《彭布罗克郡谋杀案》